LEE GANG-DU
（李康斗）
SPACE S MALL NOW OPEN
（S空間商場新開幕）
Gang-du.
康斗
MOKSAN MIDDLE SCHOOL
（木山中學）
Do you have Jae-yeong's gift?
買到彩英的禮物了嗎？
Let's go.
走吧
Mr. Lee.
李先生
If you leave now, who will finish up?
你要是走了，誰來把工作做完？
I told you a few days ago that today is my daughter's birthday.
我幾天前就跟你說了 今天是我女兒的生日
If we agree to every single thing, how will we finish on time?
要是如你所願 我們要怎麼按時完成？
I even had to bring my son here.
我甚至都把我兒子帶來幫忙了
I'll just add a steel sheet and leave.
那我去處理鋼板，之後再離開
I'll finish up soon.
我很快就會做完
Go and have some ice cream.
你去吃冰淇淋等我吧
SPACE S MALL GRAND OPENING, MARCH 2005
（S空間商場隆重開幕：2005年3月）
There's a saying people offer as a word of comfort.
有人這麼說，認為這是種安慰
"This, too, shall pass."
“這也會過去”
That's correct.
說得沒錯
MEMORIAL FOR THE VICTIMS OF THE SPACE S MALL COLLAPSE
（S空間商場 坍塌事故罹難者紀念碑）
Even the shittiest of times will pass.
就算是最艱苦的日子 最終也都會過去
IN MEMORY OF THE VICTIMS OF THE TRAGIC ACCIDENT
（以此紀念這場不幸事故的罹難者）
CHEONGYU CONSTRUCTION
（清州建設公司）
The problem is…
問題是
that it can always come back to haunt you.
它總是反反覆覆地糾纏我
You might slip.
哎呀，這樣會滑倒的
Why are you cleaning so hard this morning?
妳幹嘛一大早就清洗澡堂？
Isn't Ms. Ha Mun-su here yet?
河文秀小姐還沒來嗎？
I don't think so.
應該還沒
Give her a call.
打給她
Today is the only day this week we can go to the site.
我們這禮拜只有今天可以去工地
-See if she can-- -I'll go.
-看看她是否可以… -我可以去
I'd rather have her go herself.
我比較想要她自己去
Okay.
好吧
CASES FROM S MALL COLLAPSE DEVASTATING SCENE
（2005年S商場坍塌事故慘烈場景）
As many as 48 people.
應該是“多達”48人
Only 48 people? No.
而不是“只有”48人
As many as 48 people died.
死亡人數多達48人
Goodness! Why are you still here? What about work?
我的天哪，妳為什麼還在？ 不用上班嗎？
Tell your mom to come. Run along, I'll finish up.
去叫妳媽來，快去吧，我來完成
You have to be thorough.
-我來吧 -妳得要很仔細
I've done it before.
我做過無數次了
Aren't you going?
還不走？
Hello.
你好
PAY AT THE SALON
（請至髮廊付款）
I thought you were sick. Thankfully, you aren't.
我想說妳是不是病了，但幸好不是
So-mi sent you a message. You didn't get it?
素美傳了訊息給妳，沒收到嗎？
I got the message.
我有收到訊息
Did you not come on purpose?
妳原本不想去嗎？
Are you going to quit already?
這麼快就不幹了嗎？
I didn't even call in. I'm sorry.
我都沒打電話，很抱歉
I also came without calling, so let's call it even.
我也沒事先打電話就來找妳 所以我們扯平了
I'm sorry.
真的很抱歉
Don't be.
別這樣
I'll look clueless, like a teacher
我會裝作一無所知，就像老師
who caught a truant.
逮到不良少年一樣
I'm…
我…
I thought people keep apologizing when you're fine
妳不介意的事，別人卻跟妳道歉
made you uncomfortable.
不會讓妳不自在嗎？
-Where are we going? -To the site.
-所以我們要去哪裡？ -去工地
The place used to be a disaster site. So we need be vigilant.
那裡曾經發生過意外 所以我們一定要仔細準備
You need to make sure
妳必須要確保建築模型
the model reflects anything that can and will happen.
能反映出任何有可能會發生的問題
Don't trust the blueprint.
別相信藍圖
Temperatures were higher that year,
那一年的氣溫較高
so many cracks appeared during the curing process.
所以在固化過程中產生了很多裂縫
They had to meet the tight deadline,
因為工程期限快到了
so they did the repairs with steel sheets.
所以他們用鋼板來修補
The truss couldn't take the weight and collapsed.
桁架支撐不住重量 可能就因為這樣崩塌了
That's right.
就是這樣
-And accident killed forty… -Forty-eight people.
-那場事故死了40… -48人
No.
不對
Later, they concluded
最後的結論是藍圖的計算錯誤
And the architect took his own life.
於是建築師就自殺了
That means 49 lives were lost.
所以死亡人數是49人
BUS STOP, SPACE S MALL
（公車站：S空間商場）
Ms. Ha.
河小姐
Are you all right?
妳沒事吧？
Yes.
沒事
You should go in first. I'll be there in a moment.
你先進去，我隨後就來
It's still warm. You should drink it.
還是熱的，妳該喝點
The weather is so nice, Mun-su. Look at the sky.
姊姊，天氣好好喔，妳抬頭看天空
WE REMEMBER THEIR SOULS AND HEREBY ENGRAVE THEIR PAIN
（我們銘記他們的靈魂）
This is…
這是…
I wonder why it got shattered.
真不知道為什麼要砸碎它
My goodness…
我的天啊
There's nothing here.
這裡什麼都沒有
Nothing will happen.
不會有事的
What is she mumbling about?
她在碎碎念什麼？
Someone shattered it on purpose.
是有人故意砸壞的
It was fine just yesterday. Why is it destroyed?
昨天還好好的，怎麼就碎了呢？
Let's clean this up and assess if there's more damage.
收拾一下吧 然後去看看別的東西是否安然無恙
Yes, sir.
好的
Please don't report this to the headquarters yet.
先不要跟總公司彙報這件事
Call me if you find anything.
如果有找到什麼就立刻打給我
Of course, sir.
好，我知道了
When did you come?
妳什麼時候來的？
Let's go.
走吧
We have much to see.
我們要看的地方很多
-It wasn't just me who was offended. -Sorry?
-不是只有我很惱火 -妳說什麼？
No building owner would like it
告訴全世界這裡死過人
if you told the world that people died here.
沒有屋主會喜歡的
-Told the world? -Apparently.
-告訴全世界？ -看起來就是那樣
Why not just cover it up.
把事實掩蓋了吧
-Then-- -If we do, will the past be forgotten?
-然後… -如果這麼做
-I meant that-- -We're not just here to sell our products.
-我的意思是… -我們不只是要賣房子
Don't make it sound so easy.
別把它想得那麼簡單
Who could have done this?
會是誰砸壞的呢？
Why does a noodle place open this late?
麵店怎麼這麼晚才開門？
Not opening for lunch?
不賣午餐嗎？
NOODLES AND GIMBAP
（麵食和海苔飯捲）
Sir, you know me, right?
老闆，你認識我吧？
It's tough to forget that beat-up face.
很難忘掉你這張邋遢的臉
Then you must know how I got here, too.
那麼你一定知道我是怎麼來到這裡的
I was out of it when I got here,
我來的時候沒有意識
but tell me about the person who brought me.
但關於那個帶我來這裡的人
Who was she?
那個女生是誰？
Why do you ask?
為什麼問？
When I find out, I want to thank her.
找到她的話，我要謝謝她
I guess you work around here.
你在這附近工作吧？
Come for noodles when you're hungry.
餓了的話，就來這裡吃麵吧
Why won't he tell me? I'm even more curious now.
他幹嘛不告訴我？讓我更加好奇了
HA YEON-SU
（河妍秀）
Why do you always look a mess?
為什麼你看起來總是一團糟？
What's with your hand?
你的手怎麼了？
Just give me food.
把飯給我就好
Why do you always come here to eat?
你為什麼都來這裡吃飯？
I'm adding costs for food to your rent.
我會把伙食費加到房租裡
It was never free.
從來就不是免費的
Mom, Gang-du here…
媽媽，康斗哥…
You're older than he is.
你比他大
You always think people are older if they're taller than you. My goodness.
你總以為比你高的人 就都比你大，我的天哪
That hurt!
好痛啊
It was supposed to.
本來就是會痛的
And you! If he's too slow to figure it out,
還有你，他太遲鈍了，想不明白
you should help him, not go with it.
但你該幫他，而不是順著他
Sang-man isn't slow, he's perfectly fine.
相萬不是遲鈍，他很正常
No one acts their age these days. Right?
現在的人的行為 都跟年齡不符，不是嗎？
You'll work all night, so eat up.
你值大夜班，所以要多吃點
Work hard while you have a job.
有工作時就要勤奮工作
And don't take Sang-man to weird places
還有不要帶相萬去奇怪的地方
and give him false hopes.
讓他燃起奇怪的希望
My goodness, baby! Look at that.
我的天哪，寶貝，你看看
Okay, have some water.
好了，喝點水
Here.
來，喝水
Take your time to swallow.
慢慢吞下去
Good job.
太棒了
I want more rice.
老闆娘，我還要白飯
SANHO PUBLIC BATHS
（珊瑚公共澡堂）
Fraud?
詐欺？
Why are you making a scene after getting beaten up?
妳被人打了，為什麼要來這裡撒野？
You claim this place is a sauna,
妳說這裡是愚蠢的三溫暖
but it's no better than a bathroom!
還比不上一間浴室
Are you kidding me? Who has a bathroom this big?
妳根本不懂，誰會有這麼大的浴室？
Look, I'm bruised!
妳看，都瘀青了
The red clay in the clay room is falling apart.
黃土房的黃土都快塌下來了
I'm scared to sit in there!
坐在裡面讓我非常緊張
This place is run by women, remember?
這裡只有女員工，記得嗎？
We wanted to fix it, but we haven't had the chance.
我們想修補，但是沒時間
This is why you need men to get the work done.
這就是為什麼妳需要男人來完成工作
You always talk about men.
妳總是提到男人
Trying to tell the world that you're a gold digger?
是因為妳是拜金女嗎？
-What? -Hey!
-什麼？ -別動手
-I'll kill you! -Are you that proud of it?
-我要殺了妳 -妳很自豪嗎？
I was going to fix it. I'll do it this weekend.
我本來要修的，我這週末會修補好
Auntie, don't let customers hang underwear in the red clay room.
阿姨，別讓客人在黃土房晾內衣褲
This is a sauna, not a laundromat.
這裡是三溫暖，不是洗衣店
It's because the room gets humid.
就是因為房間受潮 黃土才會掉下來的
You're right, and they think they do nothing wrong!
妳說得對，她們還以為自己都沒做錯
This mistress not only acts like one but also talks like one, too.
我的天哪，這個拜金女 說話都沒有尊嚴
So what? What's so bad about that?
那又怎樣了？
You like being alone after your husband ran off?
妳老公跑了 妳很驕傲自己是一個人嗎？
Hey!
別說了
-Come on. -Did you hear that?
-拜託 -妳聽到了嗎？
Mun-su, did you just hear that?
文秀，妳聽到了嗎？
That's so unfair.
這很不公平耶
You and us, we go way back.
妳和我們都認識那麼久了
You should be more understanding and let things go.
妳該多體諒才是
That was a cheap shot.
這樣攻擊我媽太低級了
Your mom criticized me first.
是妳媽先在我傷疤上撒鹽的
-She called me a gold digger. -How is that criticism?
-她叫我拜金女 -那又不是缺點
Not many women can be gold diggers.
沒那麼多女人能當拜金女的
Look in the mirror. Your looks and your figure.
照照鏡子，妳的模樣和身材
Even I'd beg you to take advantage of me.
我都巴不得妳來佔我便宜
-Whose side are you on? -Yours, of course.
妳到底站在誰那邊？
You look silly like your dad,
妳看起來跟妳爸一樣蠢
but you're one sly kid.
但妳是個狡猾的孩子
He'd chuckle like that when he had nothing to say.
他不知道要說什麼時 也會這樣咧著嘴笑
He was only nice to others,
他只對別人好
but he never took care of his family.
但他從來沒有照顧好自己的家庭
He was never competent, but was always so proud.
他一直都沒什麼能力 只顧自己和他的自尊心
He ran off when things got tough.
生活艱難時，他就跑了
Why are you bringing him up now?
為什麼現在要提到他？
What's wrong? Did something happen?
怎麼了？發生什麼事了嗎？
Is he seeing someone?
他有女朋友了嗎？
What?
什麼？
DIVORCE FORM
（離婚申告書）
HA DONG-CHEOL
（河東哲）
Take that back.
把這個拿回去
I don't even want to stay married.
並不是我不想離
So you can have a proper wedding later--
這都是為了妳以後要結婚時著想
Mom, enough. I get it.
媽，夠了，我懂
Get what?
懂什麼？
Hey, you said nothing happened last night.
你說昨晚沒發生過什麼事
Why was the memorial destroyed?
那麼為什麼 那塊完好的紀念碑會被砸碎呢？
No idea.
我也想知道
It was in an odd corner and couldn't have been easy to find.
它在很偏僻的角落 所以根本不容易找到
Right? Why would anyone break it?
對吧？怎麼會有人想要破壞它呢？
Jeez, this is so frustrating.
天啊，太令人沮喪了
What will I tell management?
我要怎麼跟高層交代呢？
What if they blame me?
要是他們譴責我呢？
Come on. That's so wrong.
拜託，那樣做很不對
This site is huge.
這個工地那麼大
-One person can barely manage it at night. -Right?
晚上一個人幾乎無法應付得來
You can tell after one day, right?
只要幹過一天就知道了，對吧？
But they keep telling me to cut down on staff.
但他們還一直要我減少員工
You suffer so much day and night.
我的天哪，你日日夜夜這麼煎熬
Let's grab a beer later.
待會一起喝杯啤酒吧
A beer?
天啊，啤酒？
That sounds great. My mouth is watering.
好主意
-I'll get to work. -Okay.
-我去工作了 -好的
Don't fall asleep. Keep your eyes open.
別睡著了，打起精神
Okay, don't worry.
好的，你放心
There are no cameras on-site.
工地上沒有監視器
I also checked the entrance
我也檢查了入口處
and no one came in, other than our staff.
除了員工，沒有別人進來過
Are any of the staff suspects?
員工當中有可疑的人嗎？
We recently hired a new night guard,
我們最近請了一個新的夜間看守員
but he's a just a kid, an airhead.
但他是個滿傻裡傻氣的孩子
Please send me his information. Good work.
把他的資料傳給我，辛苦了
Don't touch a stranger without permission.
你不該隨便碰一個陌生人
The architect took his own life.
於是建築師就自殺了
That means 49 lives were lost.
所以死亡人數是49人
If we cover it up…
要是我們掩蓋事實
will the past be forgotten?
過去就不存在了嗎？
No.
不會
Come on. Mom!
真是的，媽
Mom.
媽
Mom!
媽！
Mom, what have you done?
媽，妳做了什麼？
Mom, what are you doing?
媽，妳在幹嘛？
Mom, are you okay?
媽，妳沒事吧？
Are you okay?
妳沒事吧？
-Mom! -Hey, what are you doing?
-媽 -妳在幹嘛？
Mun-su.
文秀
What's wrong with you?
妳是怎麼了？
What's wrong with me?
我怎麼了？
What the hell is wrong with you?
妳才是怎麼了？
Hey, what are you doing? Hey!
妳要幹嘛？住手
What a waste, don't throw it away. Stop!
好浪費喔，別倒掉，住手
Let me go!
放開我
Good grief!
我的天啊
Hey, Mun-su.
文秀
I won't drink it all at once.
我不會一次喝完這些酒
-I'll drink it slowly. -Let me go!
-我會一次喝一點 -放開我
What's wrong with you?
妳是怎麼了？
Give it to me.
把酒給我
-I told you to stop! -Let me go!
-我叫妳住手！ -放開我！
Goodness!
我的天哪，妳為什麼要那麼做？
Are you okay?
妳沒事吧？
How can I be okay?
我怎麼可能會沒事？
Good grief!
我的天哪
My goodness.
天啊
I couldn't sleep, so I just grabbed a drink.
我睡不著，所以喝酒了
Then I thought of that woman who complained today and your dad.
然後我想起今天那個投訴的女人 還有妳爸
So I got really mad.
所以我就很生氣
I went in the cold water to cool down--
我進冷水池裡想要讓自己冷靜…
Mom.
媽
Yes?
怎樣？
If you're going to die, tell me beforehand.
妳要去死之前，先通知我
Don't take your life without telling me!
不要沒有事先告知就去死了
What are you talking about?
妳在說什麼？
I prefer that you're sick.
我寧願妳是生病了
I'll say everything I want to say while I look after you.
然後在照顧妳的時候 我會對妳說出我想說的難聽的話
Then I'll get tired of it.
然後我會開始厭倦和疲憊
You'll be in so much pain.
妳就會很痛苦
I might want to let you go then.
那樣的話，或許我就會願意讓妳走
That sounds much better!
那樣聽起來好多了
Promise me.
答應我
Promise me, I said.
快答應我
That's nonsense.
妳這是胡說八道
Promise me.
答應我
I'm scared, Mom.
我好害怕，媽
I'm scared to death!
我怕死了！
BUS STOP, SPACE S MALL
（公車站：S空間商場）
Do you work there?
妳在那裡工作嗎？
I work there too.
我也在那裡工作
I think we've met.
我覺得我們見過
Isn't this bus stop absurd?
-這個公車站很荒謬，不是嗎？ -什麼？
Look, "Space S Mall."
妳看，“S空間商場”
It disappeared ages ago.
明明在幾年前就消失了
It's the first draft made with SketchUp.
這是用3D設計軟體做的第一份草圖
I'll finish the rendering before tomorrow's meeting.
明天的會議前，設計圖就會算好了
And the land contouring.
還有土地輪廓的測量
I revisited the site this morning,
我今早又去了工地
but I haven't measured everything yet, so it'll take a while.
但我還沒測量完 所以還需要一點時間
Good work.
辛苦了
Ms. Ha.
對了，河小姐
If you don't like this project, you may sit it out.
如果妳不喜歡這項建案 妳可以不參與
I'm not firing you.
我不是要炒妳魷魚
-You can take the Sinsu-dong project. -No.
-妳可以去接手新水洞的案子 -不要
I'll keep working on this.
我會繼續完成這個案子
You might feel uncomfortable about the accident.
妳不是因為那裡曾發生事故 感覺不自在嗎？
But I still want to do it.
但我還是想繼續
I'll do my best.
我會盡我所能
Mun-su, do you know how many cups you've had today?
文秀，妳知道 妳今天已經喝了幾杯嗎？
Your face is coffee-colored. You look awful.
妳的臉都變成咖啡色了 妳看起來糟透了
Who is that?
她是誰？
It won't be easy to begin construction on this project.
要開始建設這個案子並不簡單
We can change the purpose once the land is donated,
一旦土地捐出後 我們就可以更改使用類別
so instead of a medical center, the board will want--
所以原本的醫療中心，董事會想要…
That's exactly why I fought with my brother to take this project.
這就是為什麼 我跟我哥吵著要接管這個建案
Of course, it's all because of you.
當然，這一切都是為了你
Thanks.
謝謝
Is that all?
就這樣嗎？
Aren't you tired? Get some rest.
妳不累嗎？回去休息吧
Your mom and my brother
你媽和我哥
will tire me out even more.
最後只會讓我更累
If we were going to be a family,
如果我們是要成為一家人
we should have been first…
把我們擺在第一位會比把你媽和我爸
instead of your mom and my dad.
擺在第一位來得更好
No.
不
Your dad helped me a lot.
妳爸曾經幫了我很多忙
I could have helped you.
我本來也可以幫你
No.
不
It would have been harder.
那會更加困難
My mom doesn't like your dad,
我媽不喜歡妳爸
but I did.
但是我以前喜歡他
Why in the past tense? What about now?
為什麼是以前？現在呢？
I have to get back to work. Please excuse me.
我得回公司了，抱歉，失陪了
MOKSAN CITY HOSPITAL
（木山市立醫院）
Please hang in there.
請你忍耐一下
What are you doing?
妳在做什麼？
One second.
一下下就好
Are you out of your mind?
妳瘋掉了嗎？
Don't you know it got in his airway? Why did you push it down?
妳不知道已經進入呼吸道了嗎？ 妳還把它往裡塞？
I'm sorry.
對不起
What if that patient gets aspiration pneumonia? What then?
要是病人得了吸入性肺炎呢？
I'm sorry.
對不起
Will you say you're sorry when you kill him?
要是妳害死他 也只打算說對不起了事嗎？
Get a job as a mortician, not a doctor.
妳該從事殯葬業，而不是醫生
You've been up for 36 hours, right?
妳連續值班36小時了，對吧？
You must be dead tired.
妳一定累壞了
So who told you to schedule your week like that?
是誰叫妳這樣排班的？
You wanted to take those days off.
是妳自己要休那幾天假調班的
If you're not smart, at least stay fit to work!
要是妳不夠聰明，至少要有體力
Damn.
該死的
I knew you'd be like this.
我就知道妳會這樣
Give them to me.
給我吧
KOREA STUDENT AID FOUNDATION
（韓國獎學金基金會）
ABOUT STUDENT LOAN REPAYMENT
（學生貸款還款事宜）
LEE JAE-YEONG
（名字：李彩英）
I think your bones are fine.
我覺得沒傷到骨頭
But you might lose your nail.
但是指甲可能會剝落
You're good.
妳很厲害
I'm not. I'm just hanging on.
根本就不厲害，只是在撐而已
Find a studio apartment near the hospital.
在醫院附近找一間好的套房吧
This apartment is far and now it belongs to someone else.
這裡不但很遠 現在還是別人的房子了
Why do you pay rent to live in this dump?
妳為什麼要付錢 住在這樣的破房子裡？
Then I'll buy this house back.
到時候我會把這房子買回來
What for? That's pointless.
為了什麼？根本沒用
Mom cried so much when she sold it.
媽把它賣掉時，她哭得好傷心
Well, you wouldn't know.
當然，你不會知道
You just lay in the hospital getting mad at her.
你只是躺在醫院，對她生氣
If you live recklessly knowing how hard she tried to hold on,
明知道媽是怎麼撐過來的 你還這樣魯莽地過生活
you're a real jerk.
那你就是個混蛋
Jeez! My knees hurt.
我的天啊，膝蓋好痛
My knees are killing me.
我的膝蓋快痛死我了
My goodness.
我的天哪
Oh my.
天啊
Did you pay your respects to your mom?
你祭拜你媽媽了嗎？
I did.
有
Good.
很好
When did the young boy who pestered me to pay his mom's hospital bill
那個來纏我，要我幫忙 付他媽媽住院費的那個小男生
become a grown man?
什麼時候變成這個大人了呢？
Think of your age, Granny.
想想妳的年紀吧，奶奶
Never mind. You were already a granny back then.
不對，妳那時候就已經很老了
You little rascal. So why did you tell me to come out?
你這個小流氓，那你幹嘛叫我出來？
And you need some exercise.
而且妳該動一動身體
Sitting around all day is bad for your knees.
一整天坐著，對膝蓋非常不好
Don't worry about me. Worry about yourself.
別擔心我，擔心你自己吧
You already took everything?
你都吃完了？
You look fine on the outside, but you aren't.
你外表看起來都沒事，但你過得不好
Don't be reckless.
別魯莽度日
-I'm a lost cause. -You should be happy, you crazy kid.
我已經無可救藥了
How do I live in this crazy world with a sane mind?
我怎麼能清醒地 生活在這個瘋狂的世界呢？
Do you still see things?
你還會出現幻覺嗎？
Strengthen your mind, okay?
打起精神，好嗎？
You can take medicine for physical pain, but not for that.
你可以用藥物治療身體疼痛 但治不了那個
My goodness.
我的天啊
That stinks. Stop smoking.
那聞起來很臭，別抽了
Isn't it better than the smell of an old hag?
這比老人味好聞吧？
Want one?
要抽一根嗎？
Enjoy.
請慢用
Hey.
那個…
TO SEO YUN-OK
（收件人：徐尹玉）
-Why is this… -Exactly.
-為什麼這個… -沒錯
Why did you send it?
你幹嘛寄這個？
Are you seeing someone?
你有女朋友了？
Then why?
如果沒有，為什麼要寄？
Just keep living like this.
那就維持現狀吧
Nothing happened.
沒發生過什麼問題
Because there's nothing wrong.
就是因為沒有任何問題
-What? -Your mom and I.
-什麼？ -妳媽和我
We no longer have to fight.
我們不再需要爭吵
Nothing ever happens now.
現在什麼事都不會發生了
So let's call it quits.
所以我們就放棄吧
-Dad… -Well…
-爸 -算了吧
I heard this town will be redeveloped when construction restarts.
我聽說那邊的建設又重新開始了 這個小鎮也會重新開發
I'll close shop at the end of the year.
明年我就會把這間麵店收掉
Ten years is a long time.
十年是很長的一段時間
I feel bad for leaving you alone to deal with Mom.
我很抱歉把妳獨自留在妳媽身邊
I'm not here for an apology.
我不是來聽你道歉的
You two are still married, so you need to meet and talk it out.
你們還是夫妻 所以你們得見個面好好談談
If you avoid her all the time, that's no family.
要是你一直逃避她
She's his daughter.
她是他的女兒
My gosh.
我的天哪
Hey, are you all right?
你沒事吧？
Hey, can you give me a hand?
嘿，可以幫我一下嗎？
Do you work there?
妳在那裡工作嗎？
What was that?
你幹嘛呢？
No helmet.
沒戴安全帽
And he's a minor.
他是個未成年
He's unlicensed, and he doesn't seem insured either.
他沒駕照，看起來應該沒有保險
-Should I call the police? -No.
-要我報警嗎？ -不要
-Do you want to see a doctor?
-要去看醫生嗎？
He says no.
他說不要
Can you move? Raise your arm.
能動嗎？把手抬起來看看
Oh, no.
天啊
Look at me.
看著我
How many fingers do you see?
看到幾根手指？
What an interfering girl.
真是個多事的女人
Raise your arm.
把手抬起來
-Gosh. -Hello?
-天啊 -喂？
I have to go to work. I told them I'm running late.
我得去工作，我說了我會晚點到
Okay. Don't worry, I already called.
好的，別擔心，我已經打過電話了
My dear Gang-du.
我親愛的康斗
-What is it? -Gang-du.
什麼事？
Have you done something wrong?
妳做了什麼壞事嗎？
There are many awful moments when you're at work, don't you think?
工作的時候 會有很多不愉快的事，對吧？
Come on. What is it?
說吧，什麼事？
I feel so bad for you, my dear Gang-du.
我為你感到很抱歉，我親愛的康斗
He's here now.
他來了
Your brother is here. Say hi to him.
妳哥來了，跟他打個招呼
Okay?
好嗎？
I'm guessing you two aren't too close, even though you're siblings.
我猜你們倆的感情不是很好 雖然你們是兄妹
What is it?
有什麼事？
I mean, I want to help you make money.
我是想幫你賺錢
You make people beat you up, then harass them for money.
你讓別人打你 然後你再威脅他們給你錢
You can do it. You've got this.
妳做得到的，妳可以的
What are you doing?
妳在做什麼？
I'm sorry.
對不起
Are you kidding me? Do your best.
開玩笑嗎？用盡妳的力氣打
His pride is shattered, at least give him a chance to make money.
他的尊嚴已經碎了 所以至少給他一個賺錢的機會
Do it.
打吧
Good job.
打得好
All right. Again.
好吧，再來一次
Your guests are here. Do you need more time?
你的客人到了 你還需要更多時間嗎？
No, forget it.
不，算了吧
Not worth my time.
你什麼都不是
-Hello, sir. -Hey.
-你好 -你們好
Grab a seat.
坐下吧
-Have you had dinner? -Yes.
-吃晚飯了嗎？ -吃了
They all bow down like that,
為了生計，他們都那樣鞠躬
Do you think you're any different?
你認為你有什麼不一樣嗎？有嗎？
Mr. Jung, you should sit down first.
鄭先生，你先坐下吧
Let's go, Gang-du.
走吧，康斗
Damn.
該死的
Are you all right? I'm sorry.
你沒事吧？真的很抱歉
That was needlessly authentic.
妳根本沒必要真的打
It would have been obvious if I hadn't hit you hard. Let me see.
不用力的話 看起來明顯沒真打，讓我看看
-Damn! -Are you okay?
-該死的 -沒事吧？
So why did you wear a ring?
那麼妳幹嘛戴戒指？
Right, my ring. This thing is expensive.
對，我的戒指，這戒指很貴
Hey!
喂！
-Sorry. -Don't smile.
-對不起 -別笑
Are you all right? Why did you go in when he called?
妳還好嗎？ 為什麼他叫妳，妳就進去了？
It's work. I don't think they're human either.
這是工作，我也沒把他們當人看
I just humor them for their money.
我只是為了錢才順從他們的
That's the job.
這工作就是這樣
Here, this is yours.
拿去，這是你的
Haven't we met?
我們見過面，對吧？
I've been looking for you,
我一直在找你
and we meet here.
卻在這裡見面了
SANHO PUBLIC BATHS
（珊瑚公共澡堂）
-Mom, I got fried chicken. -You're home.
-媽，我買了炸雞 -妳回來了
Here, eat up.
來，快吃吧
What about you?
妳不吃嗎？
I feel sick from cooking it. I don't even want to smell it.
做飯時讓我覺得很膩 我甚至連味道都不想聞
You can eat.
妳多吃點
How is it?
好吃嗎？
I haven't cooked in so long, so I had no idea.
那麼久沒做飯了 我都不知道做得好不好吃
It's fine. I was hungry.
沒關係，我很餓
What's the matter? It's not good?
怎樣？不好吃嗎？
It's all right. Not all moms can be good cooks.
沒關係，不是每個媽媽 都應該要有好手藝
Darn, it was fine when I tasted it before.
天啊，我之前試吃的時候覺得還可以
You've always been a picky eater. Ever since when you were a kid.
妳從小就是個挑食鬼
What do we do?
那怎麼辦？
We'll throw in some sesame oil
還能怎麼辦？ 加點芝麻油，看要煎還是要炒
You have to finish it.
妳得負責吃完
You're awful.
妳太壞了吧
Gosh, what shall we do?
天啊，怎麼辦？
You said you got fried chicken.
-對了，妳說妳買了炸雞 -沒錯
-Let's eat this. -I made that for nothing.
-吃這個吧 -吃吧，白費工夫了
I'm so glad I got this.
真高興我買了炸雞
Let's eat.
吃吧
-This is much better. -This is it.
-這個好吃多了 -就是要吃這個
Wait.
等等
No helmet.
沒戴安全帽
And he's a minor.
他是個未成年
-Do you want to see a doctor? -No.
-要去看醫生嗎？ -不要
He says no.
他說不要
Yes, it was him.
沒錯，就是他
I can't believe it.
簡直不敢相信
He forgot that I saved him and showed off.
他忘了我救過他，還這麼跩
That's why he gets beaten up.
那就是他被別人打的原因吧
I can't believe it.
天啊，簡直無法相信
Mun-su, do you remember that tall woman who walked in like she owned the place?
文秀，妳記得那個自以為了不起地 走進來的高個子女生嗎？
-Who is she? -An exec from the head office.
-妳知道她是誰嗎？ -不是總公司的室長嗎？
No, she used to date Mr. Seo.
不是，她以前是徐代表的女朋友
-I see. -Why that response?
-原來如此 -這是什麼反應？
I knew it. They looked good together.
我就知道，他們看起來很配
so he quit and went abroad to study. Then this project…
所以他離職出國去念書 然後這個案子…
Did she regret losing him?
她後悔失去他嗎？
How absurd. Why is she back?
真可笑，她幹嘛回來？
Are the materials ready?
資料都準備好了嗎？
Should I print them or send them?
我該列印出來還是寄出去？
Let's print them out.
印出來吧
-Please let me know. -Yes, sir.
-請通知我 -是的，先生
Today's meeting will be handled by…
主持今天會議的會是…
-Is everything good to go? -All good.
-一切都準備妥當了嗎？ -都好了
I went to the women's sauna until I was eight years old.
我八歲以前都是去女子三溫暖
Sorry?
你說什麼？
My dad was too busy, so my mom lied and said I was five.
我爸太忙了，所以我媽謊稱我五歲
But I knew everything.
但是我什麼都知道
I was a tiny kid. My growth spurt came in middle school.
我小時候很矮 中學時期才開始發育的
We can't do that anymore.
現在不可以那樣做了
We have to pay a fine.
會被罰錢的
And customers don't feel at ease.
客人也會覺得不自在
I didn't feel at ease either.
那時候我也覺得不自在
I once ran into my classmate.
有一次還遇見同班的女同學
And old ladies kept trying to touch me.
那些老奶奶也會一直摸我
Some ladies are like that.
有些女人就是那樣的
Why are you telling me?
你幹嘛跟我說這個？
We're here.
我們到了
C Zone, the research unit, is 100% sustainable.
C區是研究單位 百分之百是自主永續建築區
B Zone, the silver town for the elderly, will be detached houses
B區是給銀髮族的銀色小鎮 是獨棟透天區
that are 70% sustainable.
有七成是永續建築
It all sounds great.
聽起來都很棒
It's just very expensive.
只是成本太高了
Why do you want to do art with other people's money?
為什麼要用別人的錢來搞藝術？
Let's cut costs, okay?
降低成本吧，行嗎？
These alternative energy systems
這些替代能源系統
will get 50% of the investment from state subsidies, so why not?
有五成的投資會得到政府的補助 何樂而不為？
Continue.
繼續吧
There will be a silver town retirement community
由於那是個銀色小鎮
and the doors and entrance won't be raised.
所有的門和入口都會盡量降低
We'll separate cars from pedestrians,
我們會把車道和人行道分開
so the sidewalk will be at least three meters wide.
所以人行道的寬度至少是三公尺
We'll use perforated panels on the outside
我們會在外層裝置多孔板
to make it look less ordinary and unlike any other office building.
讓它看起來沒那麼乏味 不會像普通的辦公大樓
Are you coming to dinner?
你會一起去吃晚餐吧？
Your mom is coming too. Did you get a call?
你媽也會來，沒接到電話嗎？
Yes, I heard.
有，我聽說了
One second. I'll drive us.
等我一下，我載你一起過去
No, I drove here.
不了，我開車來的
Let's go together. You can let your chauffeur--
一起去吧，你可以讓你的司機…
Excuse me.
不好意思，我先走了
I knew you'd be here.
我就知道妳會在這裡
What about dinner?
你的晚餐怎麼辦？
I still have some time left.
我還有時間
-I'm sorry about earlier. -What?
-剛剛的事很抱歉 -什麼事？
You don't take elevators, Ms. Ha. I forgot about that.
我忘了妳不喜歡搭電梯，河小姐
No, please don't let it concern you.
不，拜託你不要在意這件事
But I am concerned.
但我就是在意
Hey.
喂
Don't expect anything from him.
別對他有什麼期待
He used his mom to join our family when you left him. He's very sly.
妳離開他時
It's not like you can marry him, so just get over him already.
妳不能嫁給他，所以最好死了那條心
You married your wife for love?
你結婚是為了愛嗎？
Not all love stories end in marriage.
不是每段愛情都會步入婚姻
He's concerned?
他在意？
How dare he hit on you?
他竟敢想要把妳
These men hang around, hitting on everyone and their mothers--
這些男人無所不在 到處把妹和他們的媽媽…
Wan-jin.
婉珍
He's hitting on you.
他就是在把妳啊
Why would he hit on someone like me?
他怎麼會想跟我在一起？
He's really tall, too.
而且他真的很高大
When I stand next to him, I look like a kid.
站在他身邊，我就像個小孩一樣
Men should be short and stocky.
男人就應該要矮小和結實
Tall men make your neck hurt.
高個子的男生只會讓妳的脖子痠
Also, what's so bad about you?
還有，妳有什麼不好？
And do you think he'll be perfect?
妳以為他很完美嗎？
Look. He's rich,
妳看，他很有錢
and there's nothing he can't do.
沒有他辦不到的事
He seems like a bad boy, but he's just in love.
他看起來像壞男孩 但是他只愛一個女人
I made him,
他是我創造的
but this is nonsense. It's a lie.
但這都是扯淡，是謊言
Wan-jin…
-婉珍 -但是…
knowing these lies?
為何女人會迷戀上電視劇 或電影裡的男人呢？
Because they don't exist in real life.
現實生活中他們不存在
The men you see are incompetent and misogynistic.
妳看到的男人都是無能和厭惡女性的
If you're nice, you're a joke.
要是對他們友善，妳就是個笑話
If you turn them down, they attack you.
拒絕他們的話，他們就開始攻擊妳
They get the woman pregnant, but never take any responsibility.
搞大女人的肚子 但從來不會負起責任
What is it? What's going on?
怎麼了？發生什麼事了？
WEDDING INVITE
（婚宴邀請函）
Gi-ho's getting married?
基浩要結婚了？
Wait, are you getting married?
-等等，妳要結婚了？ -看名字啦
BRIDE: KIM SO-HYEON
（新娘：金素賢）
Weren't you two together?
你們不是在一起嗎？
I thought we were, but I guess he didn't think so.
我以為是，可是他不這麼認為
I liked him, that was it.
只是我一廂情願
So what if you liked him more?
妳比較喜歡他又怎樣？
How can he just text you like that?
他怎麼可以直接傳這個給妳？
-What a jerk. -Right?
-那個混蛋 -對吧？
Why did I like a jerk like him?
我怎麼會喜歡上像他那樣的混蛋呢？
In the end, I'm the fool.
說到底，我就是個蠢貨
Why would you go there?
為什麼要這麼想？
Because that's easier.
因為這樣比較簡單
I'll just consider myself delusional.
我只好認為自己有妄想症
I can't just call him a jerk,
我也不能罵他混蛋就消氣
so I want to attack every single man in this world.
所以我要攻擊世界上的每一個男人
I'll cuss them out tonight. You'll have a beer, right?
我今晚要詛咒他們
Let's do that. I also met this weird guy I want to cuss at.
喝吧，我也想詛咒 那個我遇到的奇怪的男生
Who?
誰？
Gang-du.
康斗哥
Hey, Sang-man. Great timing.
相萬，來得正好
Here. Aren't you going to work today?
給你，你今天不用工作嗎？
I need a day off too.
我也需要休假
What about tomorrow?
那麼明天呢？
No way. You think life is that easy?
怎麼可能？ 你以為生活有那麼簡單嗎？
May I come with you?
那麼我可以跟你一起去嗎？
-No. -Why not?
-不行 -為什麼不行？
Why do you think? I have to work.
你覺得呢？我得工作
Work on what?
做什麼？
Who?
誰？
I asked if Mr. Jung told you to do that.
我問是不是鄭先生叫你這麼做的
I have to do what he tells me to?
他叫我做什麼，我就得去做嗎？
Am I a joke?
我有這麼可笑嗎？
Then you smashed it even though no one told you to?
沒有人指使你 那麼你是自己去破壞它的？
What's going on between you and Mr. Jung?
你跟鄭先生之間是怎麼了？
And why are you here?
你為什麼會在這裡？
Hey, mister, this is my turf.
先生，這是我的地盤
You people came to my turf.
你們這些人來到了我的地盤
Why am I explaining this to you?
我幹嘛跟你解釋？
It'll be 18 million won.
一共是一千八百萬韓圓
The memorial you destroyed.
那個被你砸爛的紀念碑
I never said I did it.
我從來沒說過是我砸的
-Can you pay it back? -Why would I?
-你可以賠嗎？ -我幹嘛要賠？
It looks like you'll do time anyway, even if I report you to the police now.
看來即使我報警 你也只是去坐牢而已
Hey, shut up.
嘿，閉嘴
I'll let it go.
我可以不跟你計較
But I have one condition.
但是有一個條件
What's your job?
做什麼工作？
Something fun.
很有趣的事
I really am my mother's daughter.
真是有其母必有其女
I must be insane.
我一定是瘋掉了
Auntie, you're the best. Thanks.
阿姨，妳最棒了，謝謝
What about Mom?
我媽呢？
Really? What's going on?
真的嗎？發生什麼事了？
Of course. It's best to have no trouble.
當然，沒有麻煩是最棒的了
Okay.
好的
What?
什麼？
Mun-su, you're late.
文秀，妳遲到了
I'm sorry. Did you see the guy who just walked in? Who is he?
很抱歉，妳有看見 那個剛走進來的男生嗎？他是誰？
My goodness. Why is your face red?
天啊，妳的臉怎麼那麼紅？
-Are rough guys your type? -So-mi.
-原來妳喜歡粗獷型的 -素美
Someone from the site.
他在工地工作
We need someone to check the progress once we begin construction.
工程一旦開始 我們就需要有個人來檢查進度
Maybe he found someone.
所以或許請了他
Wait, you reek of alcohol.
等等，妳有一股難聞的酒味
Mun-su, today is your worst day ever since I met you.
文秀，今天是我認識妳以來 妳看起來最糟糕的一天
You're terrible up close.
近距離看妳，妳真是太可怕了
You'll age in an instant. Your pores are already this…
妳會老得很快 妳的毛孔都已經這樣…
-What? -Before you criticize my appearance,
-怎樣？ -在妳批評我的樣貌之前
look in the mirror first.
請妳先去照照鏡子
I thought about your offer.
我考慮過你的提議
Do I have to be a spy?
我必須得當間諜嗎？
In a way, yes.
某個程度上說，沒錯
Why do you trust me? That's a job for an insider.
你為什麼會信任我？
A money-based relationship is more trustworthy.
用金錢交易的合作關係更加值得信賴
I have minimal on-site experience.
我在工地的經驗只是皮毛
I don't have a good grasp of the situation.
我不認為我有能力掌握情況
Just record everything that happens on-site.
你只需要記錄工地上發生的所有事
I'll be the judge.
由我來做判斷
Why do you have to do this?
你為什麼一定要這麼做？
In the accident 12 years ago,
12年前的坍塌事故中
a total of 11 people died on-site.
工地裡有11位工人喪命
Do you know what's funny?
你知道有趣的是什麼嗎？
The people who said there were no problems weren't there.
當時那些說工程沒問題的人 都不在那裡
The ones who raised the issue were criticized,
提出問題的人卻遭到批評
stayed behind to fix the problems and became victims.
只有留下來補救問題的人成了受害者
People who only wanted to grab some soju after work.
而那些人只是希望下班後 可以喝點燒酒罷了
I won't let it happen.
我不會讓那樣的事發生
Are you saying there's a problem with this project too?
你是說這個建案也有問題嗎？
No.
不是
I want to prevent problems before they arise.
我要在問題出現以前，先做好預防
Agreed.
成交
You're a cool guy.
你很酷
LEE GANG-DU
（李康斗）
You didn't ask why I destroyed it.
你沒問我為什麼要砸掉紀念碑？
I don't care about the past.
我不在乎過去
Everything you say will be an excuse.
無論你說什麼都是藉口
I'm more concerned with what you'll do from now on.
對我來說，重要的是 你從今以後會做的事
HONEY WATER
（蜂蜜水）
You smell.
妳很臭
You still reek of alcohol.
還是能聞到酒味
We meet again.
又見面了
Do you work at Seowon?
妳在水原工作嗎？
We'll see each other often.
以後我們會經常見面的
Hey.
喂
Since you're in this business, let me be clear.
既然你入了這一行，讓我把話說清楚
Don't do that on-site.
別在工地那樣做
You can put everyone in danger with one mistake you make.
你在工地上只要犯一個錯誤 每個人就都會有危險
You should trust people and help out even if it's not your job.
相信每個人，伸出援手 就算那不是你的工作
Help out with what?
幫忙做什麼？
You shouldn't be too trusting and careless.
妳不該過度相信別人和粗心大意
I should trust people around me when I'm in danger?
有危險時，該相信身邊的人嗎？
I don't want to.
我不會那麼做
Over here.
我在這裡
Hey, there's a survivor.
那裡有生還者
-A survivor! -Over here. We have a survivor.
-有生還者 -在這裡，我們找到生還者
-We have a survivor! -A survivor. Hurry!
-我們找到一個生還者 -有生還者，快
Move it out!
把它拉開
Move out! Be careful!
拉開，小心點
I'm here!
我在這裡
I'm right here!
我就在這裡
When faced with death,
當我們面對死亡時
everyone becomes selfish.
每一個人都是自私的
-I'm going to need to touch you. -What?
-讓我抱妳吧 -你幹嘛這麼做？
Just say thank you.
妳只要說聲謝謝就行了
Are you two close?
你們兩個很熟嗎？
Yes. Why can't I know girls?
對，我不該有女性朋友嗎？
Are you ignoring me? Is that necessary here?
妳故意不理我嗎？有這個必要嗎？
You two know each other?
你們兩個私底下認識嗎？
-Yes. -No.
-沒錯 -不認識
We're drawn to bad boys instead of good boys.
我們必定會被壞男孩吸引 而不是好男孩
It's okay. I don't like sweet things.
沒關係，我不喜歡吃甜食
But this is good.
但是這個很好吃
I'll have a bite.
那就吃一口吧
-You weren't going to tell? -It was nothing.
妳不想告訴我嗎？
it's not a good feeling to find out from someone else.
從別人口中聽到妳的事
I'm sorry. I crossed the line.
對不起，我越權了
Keep crossing it.
妳可以繼續越權
He asked if you'll rebuild the memorial or not.
她問說你會不會重新做一個紀念碑
Do you think she knows you're the one…
李先生，紀念碑是你破壞的
Grab my hand.
抓住我的手
…who smashed the memorial?
你覺得她知道嗎？